(Imperial Video Screening Room)
（皇朝录像厅）
(Restroom)
（卫生间）
(Chlorpromazine Hydrochloride Injection)
（盐酸氯丙嗪注射液）
Who is it?
谁呀？
Hualin Public Security Bureau.
桦林公安局的
Ma Desheng.
马德胜
We've met before, in Hualin.
咱们在桦林见过
I remember you, Captain Ma.
有印象，马队长
What brings you to Songhe?
怎么到松河来了？
I was just passing through.
这不是正好路过吗？
I'm here to ask you a few things about Shen Mo.
沈墨的事，我来跟你了解点情况
Come in.
请进
This way, please.
来，这边请
Have a seat.
坐这
A big tiger.
大老虎
Looks fierce.
挺凶啊
Borrowing the tiger's might, are we?
狐假虎威吧
How else do you catch tiger cubs without entering the tiger's den?
还不入虎穴，焉得虎子呢
You've got a line for everything.
一套一套的
Captain Ma.
马队长
Sorry to intrude.
打扰了啊
Have a seat.
你坐啊
Smoke?
抽烟吗？
I quit.
戒了
Shen Mo...
沈墨…
How old was she when she came to live with you?
几岁和你们一起生活的呀？
You've asked me before.
你问过我
Not quite nine.
九岁不到
Under nine.
不到九岁
How was your relationship?
你们关系怎么样？
Did you talk much, day to day?
平时交流得多吗？
What relationship? We're family.
啥关系？ 一家人
Why so tense?
怎么紧张呀？
Having a cop in the house feels awkward, right?
警察进家里别扭是不？
It's fine, just chatting.
没事，瞎聊聊
Why not stay for a drink at noon?
要不中午你在这喝口？
No, I'm just here for a quick chat.
没有，我就瞎聊两句
It's just, there's this case.
这不这案子在这呢
It's... it's troubling.
它也…它也愁
About her...
她这个…
Before she went to college in Hualin, did she ever date anyone?
去桦林上大学之前，谈过恋爱吗？
As far as I know,
据我了解
no.
没有
No.
Which room was hers? Mind if I take a look?
她住哪屋？ 我能瞅瞅不？
Is that all right?
方便不？
It's fine.
方便
This room?
这屋啊？
This room.
这屋
No one lives in this room now?
这屋现在没人住啊？
No.
是
Since Momo left,
墨墨走了
the room's been empty.
这屋子就空了
Nice piano.
钢琴不错
It's Shen Mo's, isn't it?
这是沈墨的吧？
You spared no expense.
挺舍得花钱呀
We raised her like our own daughter.
当亲闺女养的嘛
Have some water.
喝口水吧
喝口水
Thanks.
谢谢
You raised Shen Mo so well.
把沈墨养得这么好
Weren't you afraid she'd run into bad people?
不怕她碰到坏人啊？
Captain Ma, the way you talk...
马队长，你这嗑唠的
Isn't that what you police are for?
不是还有你们警察吗？
(Labor Union)
（工会）
You work at the No. 2 Textile Mill, right?
我记着你在二纺厂工作是吧？
Yes, I drive for the labor union.
对，在工会开车
Let's talk somewhere else.
咱俩换个地唠唠
This money order matures on the 17th.
这张汇票的承兑日期是17号
Which is today.
也就是今天
The bank opens at nine.
银行九点钟上班
I'll take one team inside the bank.
我带一组人在银行里
Two more teams cover the north and south intersections.
南北、两个路口由两组人守住
A sum this large,
这么大一笔钱
whoever dared go once will surely go a second time.
这个人敢去第一次 就一定会再去第二次
Besides the bank,
除了银行
the train station, the bus station — every transit hub in and out of Hualin
火车站、汽车站 所有能出入桦林的交通枢纽
is already staffed in advance.
都已经提前安排好人了
Today, no one gets out of Hualin.
保证今天谁也跑不出桦林
Who let you in?
谁让你进来的？
I'm looking for Captain Ma.
我找马队
Master Wang.
王师傅
Outside.
门口
Director Zhu.
朱局
A moment, outside.
门口一下
You... go on.
你…你接着说
Captain Ma went to Songhe yesterday.
马队昨天去松河了
Did he say when he'd be back?
没说啥时候回来？
He should be back tonight.
今天晚上应该能回来
What is it? You can tell me.
啥事？ 你跟我说吧
Fine, later then.
行，完了再说
Everything okay?
没事？
It's fine.
没事
What've you got there?
拿的啥呀？
Groceries from the market.
菜市场买菜
-Really nothing?
-Nothing...
-真没事？
-没事…
Look at you, drenched in sweat.
你瞅你这一脑袋汗
Walked too fast. Go on back.
走急了，回吧
-Really nothing?
-Nothing. Go back.
-真没事？
-没事，回去吧
Yang'er.
阳儿
Want something to eat?
吃点不？
I'll fry you an egg.
妈给你煎个鸡蛋
Mom.
妈
I feel awful.
我难受
Where does it hurt?
哪难受啊？
My head aches.
头疼
Did you bump it yesterday?
是不是昨天磕着了呀？
Let me see.
我看看
Did you hit it somewhere?
是不磕哪了？
Have some water.
喝点水
Let Mom rub it for you.
妈给你按按啊
What kind of pain is it?
是怎么疼法啊？
Is it throbbing, or does it come in waves?
是一跳一跳的还是一阵一阵疼？
Throbbing.
跳着疼
I just slept badly.
就是没睡好
Here, eat something.
来，吃点东西啊
-Come on.
-I'm not hungry.
-来
-我不饿
The way you're...
你这么…
Not eating, not drinking — how could you not be hungry?
不吃不喝的，能不饿吗？
Don't cry, Mom.
妳别哭啊，妈
I'm fine.
我没事
Trussed up like this, how could you be fine?
谁这么五花大绑能没事？
Mom, loosen these for me a little.
妈，妳帮我松快松快吧
Okay.
好
Your hands...
这手
Yang'er.
阳儿
Your dad's not here.
你爸没在
Tell Mom.
你跟妈说说吧
What's really wrong with you?
你到底怎么的了？
Mom.
妈
I want a bowl of water-rinsed rice.
我想吃碗水捞饭
Okay, Mom will go make it.
行，妈给你做去啊
Here, Yang'er.
来，阳儿
Eat slowly.
你慢点吃
Mom.
妈
My quilt feels a bit thin.
我那被子好像有点薄
It gets drafty at night.
夜里有点飕得慌
Didn't I just switch you to a thick quilt the other day?
这前两天不刚给你换了厚被子吗？
Maybe the cotton's shifted out of the corner.
可能被角的棉花跑了
Let me check, I'll find you another one.
那我看看，再给你找一床啊
Mom.
妈
I'm sorry.
对不起
Yang'er... what are you doing?
阳儿…你干啥？
Yang'er, open the door.
阳儿，你开门
Yang'er... let Mom out.
阳儿…你让妈出去
Yang'er, whatever you do, don't run.
阳儿，你千万别跑
Whatever it is, wait until your dad's back.
你有啥事，等你爸回来再说啊
Yang'er.
阳儿
Mom.
妈
I have to go out.
我必须得出去一趟
I made this mistake; I have to fix it myself.
我自己犯的错，我得自己解决
Wait for me.
妳等着我
I'll come back, I promise.
我一定回来
Yang'er... don't run.
阳儿…你别跑
Yang'er, open the door.
阳儿，你开门
Wang Yang...
王阳…
Open the door, Wang Yang...
你开开门呀，王阳…
Wang Yang, don't run.
王阳，你别跑
Wang Yang.
王阳
Wang Yang, open the door.
王阳，开门呀
Wang Yang...
王阳…
Where's Wang Yang?
王阳呢？
He ran. I couldn't hold him.
跑了，没看住
How could you not even keep an eye on him?
妳怎么连个人都看不住？
What do we do?
怎么办啊？
Where do we even look?
上哪找去啊？
Stop wailing.
别嗷嗷了
Let me think.
我想想
Hello?
喂？
Please page 9652827.
请呼9652827
Say, "Wang Xiang has important information to report.
说“王响有重要情况汇报
Please call back at once."
请速速回电”
Do you have children, Captain Ma?
你有孩子吗，马队长？
As a cop, you see too many bastards.
当警察王八蛋见得太多
Would you dare have any?
敢生吗？
True enough.
也是
I have a son too, named Shen Hui.
我还有个儿子，叫沉辉
Honestly, my feelings for Momo...
其实我对墨墨…
I care more for Momo than for that son.
对墨墨的感情比对这个儿子感情深
You know,
你知道
this child lost both her parents.
这孩子爹妈都没了
I raised her for ten years.
在我这养了十年呀
Ten years.
十年
You could say
可以这么讲
I gave her the very best.
我把最好的都给了她
Good food, good clothes.
好吃、好穿
I even bought her a piano.
我还给她买了钢琴
Once you bring it up,
一提这个呀
I can't even...
不能提…
No man in this world could ever be as good to her as I was.
这个世上没有任何一个男人 能像我对她这么好
No one.
没有
Good in what way?
哪种好啊？
Someone took nude photos of Shen Mo and wrote a denunciation letter.
有人给沈墨拍裸照，写举报信
Posted it right on the notice board at Hualin Medical.
就贴在桦医的宣传栏上
You must know about this, right?
这事你肯定知道吧？
Who could do such a thing?
谁能干出这样的事来呀？
Could it be someone close to her?
不会就是她身边的人吧？
Wanting to control her, taking nude photos.
想控制她，拍裸照
Treating her like a plaything.
把她当玩物
And Shen Mo didn't dare resist.
沈墨又不敢反抗
A child grows up one day.
孩子总有长大的一天
She'd surely want to break free of that control.
肯定是想摆脱这种控制
But that person wouldn't have it.
可这个人就不干了
Wouldn't you say such a person deserves to die a thousand deaths?
你说这人是不是罪该万死？
Captain Ma, if you have something to say, say it straight.
马队长，你有什么你就直说
Don't beat around the bush.
别绕弯子
There's a kettle in that photo, isn't there?
这照片上不是有个水壶吗？
Doesn't it look familiar?
看着是不是挺眼熟？
I saw an identical one in your house.
我在你们家看着个一模一样的
Explain that to me.
你给我解释解释这事
This kettle?
就这水壶啊？
You're really something.
你可真招笑
At our No. 2 Textile Mill, every household has one just like it.
在我们二纺厂 家家户户都有这么一把
What you want to ask me is
你是想问我
whether I took that photo, right?
这照片是不是我拍的吧？
Did you take it?
是不是你拍的？
You're a policeman.
你是警察
How can you even ask me that?
你怎么还能问我呢？
Let me tell you, Shen Dongliang,
我告诉你，沉栋梁
I'll investigate this case to the very end.
这案子我会一查到底
Not just the murderer —
不光是杀人凶手
any monstrous, evil deed, I'll pursue to the very end.
任何伤天害理的事，我都会一查到底
Good, then I'm reassured.
好，那我就放心了
When you've cracked it,
到时候你查明白了
I'll send you a banner of honor.
我给你送个锦旗
Don't be in such a hurry.
别着急呀
Once we're in Hualin, we'll talk at leisure.
到了桦林，咱慢慢聊
Sure.
好啊
In Hualin,
到桦林
in Hualin, when I meet your superiors,
到桦林我跟你们领导
I'll ask them properly:
见了面我好好问一问
as a people's policeman,
你作为人民警察
how exactly do you serve the people?
你是怎么为人民的？
Like this... just like this,
就这…就这么
shoving a victim's family member into a car to interrogate him without authorization.
擅自地把受害人的家属 怼到车里来讯问
I really must ask your superiors
我到底要问问你们领导
whether this befits the conduct of a people's policeman,
这符不符合一个人民警察的行为
whether it's in line with your... your regulations.
符不符合你们…你们的规定
You know what I regretted most back then?
我当时最遗憾的你知道是什么吗？
You know what I regret most of all?
我最后悔的你知道是什么吗？
What I regret most is
我最后悔的就是
that she didn't die by my hand.
她没死我手里
Look at that.
你看看
Back then,
那时候
so pure.
多干净啊
You fucking animal.
你他妈个畜生你
You're not even human.
不是人的玩意
Get out.
下来
Get over here.
给我过来
Pure?
干净？
Damn.
我去
Go.
去
Damn.
我去
Fuck.
操
我操
Fuck.
操
This is all you've fucking got?
你他妈就这么大点能耐了？
Can't crack the case, huh?
查不明白案子是吧？
So you take it out on the victim's family?
就拿受害人家属撒气呀？
Come on...
来…
Still fucking putting on an act.
他妈还装呢
The police are beating people!
警察打人了
Somebody, help!
来人啊
The police are beating people!
警察打人了
Damn.
我去
Fuck.
操
Ma Desheng.
马德胜
This case,
这案子
you can't solve it.
你破不了
Do you know what they call...
知道啥叫…
Do you know what "dead men tell no tales" means?
你知道啥叫死无对证吗？
You fucking...
你他妈的
Come on...
来…
Come on.
来
Boss, another plate of dumplings.
老板，再来一份饺子
Do you remember when we were kids,
妳还记不记得咱俩小时候
how at night when I was hungry I'd sneak into the kitchen for food?
晚上我饿了去厨房偷东西吃？
Dad caught me and was going to hit me,
咱爸看见了要打我
but you insisted it was you who ate it.
妳非说是妳吃的
In the end Dad gave me a beating anyway.
结果咱爸打了我一顿
Why bring this up all of a sudden?
怎么突然说这个？
These dumplings taste just like the ones from back then.
这个饺子和小时候吃的味道一样
My stomach's upset.
我肚子不舒服
I'm going to the restroom; wait for me here.
我去下厕所，妳在这等我
Do you want anything else to eat?
妳还要吃什么吗？
Cheer up.
开心点
Smile.
要笑
One moment, please.
您稍等一下
Wire 200.
汇200
Boss, the check.
老板，结帐
Don't move...
别动…
Hold him down.
摁住
Cuff him...
铐上…
-Hold him down.
-Cuff him.
-摁住
-铐上
Behave.
老实点
(If I don't come back, leave with Wang Yang)
（如果我没回来，跟王阳一起走）
(I'll take all the blame)
（我会承担一切）
Move...
走…
What's the matter, Master Wang?
怎么的了，王师傅？
Last time you said
你上回说
you'd repay me if I introduced you to Huang Liru.
让我介绍黄丽茹给你，完了报答我
Does that still stand?
这个事算数不？
It stands.
算数啊
Play it right and you might end up my brother-in-law.
整不好以后你都我姐夫了
Of course it stands.
必须算数
Here's your chance.
机会来了
Come catch someone with me tonight.
晚上跟我去抓人
Catch who?
抓谁呀？
My son.
我儿子
The boy's been led astray by a bunch of bad kids.
这小子被一帮坏孩子给带坏了
Tonight they might run off together.
晚上没准一起跑
No, Master Wang, you don't get it.
不，王师傅，你不知道
These half-grown kids nowadays, they hit hard.
就现在那半大小子，下手挺黑
If it comes to blows,
你这要咔咔弄起来
the two of us might be no match.
咱俩未必是对手
What are you saying?
你啥意思？
Why not give Captain Ma a heads-up?
要不你给马队长打个招呼？
Have him send two men along with us.
让他派两人跟着咱俩
Can't reach Captain Ma.
马队联系不上
Does my sister know about this?
那咱家我姐知道这事不？
If you're going to marry Liru,
你要娶丽茹
not only is my wife your sister,
不光我媳妇是你姐
my son is your nephew too.
我儿子也是你外甥
An uncle's word carries weight.
娘亲舅大
Are you in or not?
这事管不管？
I'm in.
我管
-For my own nephew, I have to be.
-Good.
-为我亲外甥，我必须管
-好
Tell me, how do I help?
你说吧，怎么帮？
-How's it going?
-Watch this — here, one for you, here.
-怎么样？
-看着，来…给你来一个，来
What's that?
啥玩意？
Hello.
你好
Could you tell me which room Gong Biao lives in?
我想问一下龚彪住哪屋呀？
-Gong Biao — Biaozi?
-Yes.
-龚彪，彪子吗？
-对
-The one from the plant office?
-Yes.
-厂办那个？
-对
Turn left, room two-two-two.
左拐，三个二
Okay, thanks.
好，谢谢啊
Haven't we met somewhere?
咱俩是不是在哪见过？
Have we?
见过吗？
I don't remember.
我怎么没印象啊？
Aren't you a nurse at the plant hospital?
妳是不是厂医院的护士？
You gave me a shot once — it didn't hurt at all.
妳给我打过针，妳打的一点都不疼
Really?
是吗？
What's with your attitude?
你什么态度呢？
What's with the attitude?
什么态度呢？
Hear me? Don't you point fingers at me.
听见没？ 别给我指指点点的啊
Biaozi.
彪子
Hey, stop knocking.
不是，别敲了
Didn't I say no games today?
我不说今天不玩了吗？
Someone's here for you, hurry.
有人找你，快点
Who is it?
谁呀？
Liru, what brings you here?
丽茹，妳怎么来了？
Heading out?
要出去呀？
Is this a good time?
方便吗？
If it's not, I'll come back later.
要是不方便的话，我就先回去了
It's fine...
方便…
Come... come in.
妳进…进屋吧
What are you coming in for?
你进来干啥呀？
We know each other, just gonna chat.
俺俩认识，唠唠嗑吧
Chat about what? Get lost...
唠啥唠呀？ 走吧…
You people are really warm.
你们这人可真热情
Warm, my foot.
热情啥？
Young workers.
青工
Didn't even finish middle school, no manners.
国中都没毕业呢，没啥素质
Have a seat, Liru.
妳坐呀，丽茹
I keep telling them,
总跟他们强调
I say, mind the housekeeping...
我说注意内务…
these few punks keep coming to wreck my place.
就这几个小子总跑我这搞破坏
Sit.
坐
All clean.
干净了
Let me pour... pour you some water.
我给妳倒…倒杯水喝
Okay.
好
It's clean.
干净的
Thanks.
谢谢
-Too hot? I'll add some cold water.
-It's fine...
-是不烫呀？ 我给妳加点凉水
-没事…
I brought a handkerchief.
我有带手绢
Did you come to see me about something?
妳找我有事啊？
It's nothing really.
其实也没啥事
It's just, these past few days,
就是我这几天嘛
I keep having dreams.
老爱作梦
Dreams about what?
作啥梦啊？
I forget where I read this line,
我忘了我在哪看到那么一句话
but it was quite philosophical.
说得挺有哲理的
Roughly it means...
大概意思就是…
the person who appears in your dream,
梦里出现的人
the moment you wake, you should go see them.
你醒过来马上就要去见他
Life is that simple.
生活就是这么简单
"The Lovers on the Bridge."
《新桥恋人》
A French film.
法国片
You know so much.
你懂的可真多
Oh, right.
对了
That book about dreams you mentioned last time,
上回你说那本跟作梦有关的书
could I borrow it?
能借我看看吗？
"The Interpretation of Dreams."
《梦的解析》
By Freud, of Austria.
奥地利，佛洛伊德作
If you want it, I'll find it for you.
妳要，我找给妳
If there's one thing I have, it's books.
我这就是书多
-Is it hard to find?
-It's fine.
-好找吗？
-没事
If it's too much trouble, never mind.
要是太费劲就算了
It's fine...
没事…
I even flipped through a couple pages before bed last night.
我昨晚睡前我还…我还翻两页呢
My books are such a jumble.
我这书太杂了
You okay?
没事吧？
I'm fine...
没事…
Did you hurt yourself?
碰哪了？
Here... come on, let me help you up, come.
来…你过来，扶你走，来
What's wrong?
怎么了？
Something's in my eye.
好像迷眼了
Sit still...
坐好…
Let me look.
我看看
Which eye?
哪只眼睛啊？
This one.
这个
Any better?
好点没？
No, blow on it again.
没好，妳再吹一吹
Now?
这回呢？
What is it?
怎么的了？
You smell so nice.
妳身上味真好闻
Smell like what?
啥味啊？
Like disinfectant.
消毒水味
What the heck?
什么玩意呢？
Hello, could you find Gong Biao for me?
你好，你帮我找一下龚彪
Room two-two-two, from the plant office.
三个二，厂办的
There you are.
在这呢
No wonder I couldn't find you.
我说怎么找不着呢
Biaozi.
彪子
You love studying too much.
你太爱学习了
It's a habit.
习惯了
Arming yourself with knowledge.
用知识武装自己
Wait, we haven't even made things official yet.
不是，咱俩还没确定关系
Isn't this improper?
这样不合适吧？
Let me ask you,
我问你
do you love me?
你爱我吗？
I do.
我爱
If you love me, it's proper.
爱我就合适
Biaozi, there's a call for you at the front desk.
彪子，传达室有你电话来
Tell them I'm not here.
你说我不在
He didn't say where he went?
他没说上哪去啊？
Didn't leave any message before he left?
临走也没留个话啥的？
Okay, thanks.
好，谢谢
Unreliable.
不着调
Stop.
站住
Don't move.
别动啊
I've got a weapon for self-defense here.
我手里可带着防身工具呢
Where's Wang Yang?
王阳呢？
I know you're in this together.
我知道你们是一伙的
The police are coming any minute.
警察马上就来了
When the police get here,
等警察来了
your attitude will change.
就不是这个态度了
Turn around.
转过来
Tie yourself up.
把自己捆上
Stop.
站住
Can you please...
你们能不能…
let Wang Yang go?
放过王阳？
What do you want?
你们想要啥？
As long as you let Wang Yang go,
只要放过王阳
I... I'll agree to anything.
我…我什么都能答应
Don't worry.
你放心
I'll keep my mouth shut.
我嘴肯定严
As long as you let Wang Yang...
只要把王阳…
go, I... I won't say a word.
放了，我…我什么都不会说
I'm begging you.
我求你了
He's our only precious son.
我们就这么一个宝贝儿子
His mother's worried sick at home.
他妈在家都急死了
His mother has a heart condition.
他妈有心脏病
She can't take the shock.
受不了刺激
Besides, I promised her
另外，我答应她
I'd bring Wang Yang home today.
今天带王阳回去
I'm begging you.
我求你了
I'm sorry.
对不起
Wang Yang is all I have.
我只有王阳了
I'm sorry.
对不起
It's okay.
没事啊
Where have you been all these days?
你们这些天去哪了？
I thought something had happened to you.
我以为妳出事了呢
Why are you alone?
怎么就妳自己呀？
Where's Weijun?
军儿呢？
He got caught.
他被抓了
Come back with me.
妳跟我回去吧
What did you say?
你说什么？
I've made up my mind.
我想好了
Let's go back.
咱们回去吧
I'll turn myself in.
我去自首
Why?
为什么？
Didn't we agree to leave together?
咱们不是说好一起走的吗？
You can't spend your whole life a fugitive.
妳不能一辈子当逃犯呀
If you go back now, you still have a chance.
现在回去妳还有机会
It's too late, Wang Yang.
来不及了，王阳
I can't go back.
我回不去了
It's not too late.
来得及
We'll say the Lu Wenzhong thing was all me.
就说卢文仲的事都是我干的
I killed him.
人是我杀的
I disposed of the body too.
尸体也是我处理的
It has nothing to do with you.
跟妳没关系
You can still go on with school.
妳还能继续上学
Still play piano.
还能弹钢琴
Still become a doctor.
还能当医生
If I somehow make it out alive,
要是我还能活着的话
wait for me.
妳就等着我
I killed Yin Hong.
我杀了殷红
The "me" they think they know
他们以为的我
is Yin Hong.
是殷红
I killed Yin Hong.
殷红是我杀的
Wang Yang, you're all I have.
王阳，我只有你了
Didn't we agree
我们不是说好
to find a new place together,
一起找一个新的地方
and live all over again?
重新活一次吗？
Wang Yang, you're all I have.
王阳，我只有你了
Come away with me.
你跟我一起走吧
I understand now.
我明白了
You and I aren't the same after all.
你和我还是不一样
You have your home.
你有你的家
You have your parents.
你有你爸妈
I have nothing left.
我什么都没有了
Master Wang.
王师傅
Sorry about that, Master Wang.
对不住啊，王师傅
Something came up last minute and held me up.
我临时有点事，绊住脚了
Your wife said you weren't home.
嫂子说你不在家
So I came out to meet you.
我想着出来迎迎你
Want me to take over your shift?
要倒班不？
I'll... I'll keep watch a while.
我…我盯一会去
How'd you get so filthy?
你怎么整得脏兮兮的？
What happened?
怎么整的？
It's nothing.
没事
Got myself caught on something.
自己卡的
Biaozi.
彪子
I need a favor.
求你个事
Between us, no need to ask.
咱俩之间啥求不求的？
What is it?
啥事啊？
It's about this business with our Wang Yang.
就是我们家王阳那事
Don't tell anyone, all right?
和谁都别说，好不好？
Don't worry, my lips are sealed.
你放心，我嘴肯定严实
Where's Wang Yang?
王阳呢？
Don't ask. Go on home.
别问了，回去吧
Where's Yang'er?
阳儿呢？
Where's my boy?
孩子呢？
No, say something.
不，你说话呀
Where did the boy go?
孩子哪去了？
Yang'er ran off.
阳儿跑了
Did you run into him?
你碰上他了？
I didn't run into Yang'er.
我没碰着阳儿
The one I ran into was probably his accomplice.
我碰见的可能是他的同伙
No, how... how could you let him get away?
不是，怎么…怎么能让他跑了呢？
You said you'd surely bring him...
你不说你肯定能把他…
Stop wailing at me, my head hurts.
妳别给我嗷嗷了，我脑袋疼
No, he can't have run.
不是，他不能跑
He told me to wait for him at home.
他跟我说他让我在家等他
Oh God.
妈呀
Where could that boy have gone?
这孩子能跑哪去呀？
Where'd he run to?
他跑哪？
Here.
来
Here... take your medicine.
来…吃药
Take your medicine.
吃药
Take it... here.
吃药…来
Don't overthink it.
妳别多想啊
Yang'er's surely fine.
阳儿肯定没事
No, I'm going out to look for him again.
不行，我一会我出去再找他
Take your medicine.
把药吃了
Promise me.
你答应我
Bring my son back to me.
你把儿子给我领回来
Don't worry.
妳放心
Our son's sharp.
咱儿子精明
Wherever he ends up, once he's settled,
他走到哪，落脚之后
he'll surely contact us.
肯定会联系我们
Then we'll go bring him home together.
到时候我们一起把他接回来
Here, take your medicine.
来，把药吃了
Lie down a while, rest and calm down.
妳得躺会，躺会静一静
What are you doing?
妳干啥呀？
I'm reheating the food.
我把菜热热
When the boy comes back, he'll be eating cold food.
一会孩子回来，吃凉饭了
(Hualin Steel)
（桦林钢铁）
(Hualin Steel No. 1 Main Plant Workers' Congress)
（桦林钢铁第一总厂职工代表大会）
Why polish it so bright?
擦那么亮干啥呀？
The trains don't even run anymore.
火车也不跑了
People are at fault, not the engine.
人有错，它没错
When I see it all grimy,
我看它脏兮兮的
it pains my heart.
我心里难受
Quanli's not coming either.
这全力也不来了
Hauling loads for someone, he crushed his leg.
帮人拉活，把腿给砸坏了
All for his wife and kids.
那都是为了老婆、孩子
This time when they announce the layoff list,
这回宣布下岗名单
I'll be first on it in the locomotive depot.
机务段我排头一个
It won't be you.
轮不上你
I'll definitely be ahead of you.
我肯定排在你前头
Let's go, Master Wang.
走吧，王师傅
The music's already playing.
歌都放起来了
You go ahead.
你先过去
I'll come once I've finished polishing.
我擦完了就过去
Not going to hear the list?
不听名单了？
It was decided long ago.
早就定好的事了
What difference does hearing it make?
听不听有啥两样的？
I'll go listen.
我听听吧
Biaozi.
彪子
Don't go shouting.
你别瞎喊
What've you got in your hand?
手里拿的啥呀？
The layoff list?
下岗名单啊？
Let me have a peek.
我瞅一眼
No, can I just let you peek at a confidential document?
不，机密文件能随便让你们瞅吗？
From now on, stop yelling "Biaozi, Biaozi" in public.
以后在外面别老喊彪子彪子啊
-Show some respect.
-Fine.
-注意点分寸
-行
After the meeting, he's getting promoted.
一会开会人提拔了
Sure, Director Biao.
行，彪主任
Don't talk nonsense.
别瞎说
Until the official red-header order comes down, it's not official, got it?
红头文件没下来都不算数，知道不？
In a few days I'll set something up at Canteen No. 2.
过几天我在二食堂安排
Everyone come, all right?
到时候大伙都到啊
Set up what?
安排啥呀？
A wedding banquet.
喜酒吧
Liru and I are about to register our marriage.
我跟丽茹马上要领证了
Huang Liru?
黄丽茹？
The one from the plant hospital?
厂医院那个？
Who else would it be?
那还能有谁呀？
Would I settle for just anyone?
一般人我能看上吗？
That scarf of yours is pretty snazzy.
你这围脖整得挺带劲啊
Liru bought it.
丽茹买的
It's part of a set, see?
这不一套的吗？
Nice color.
色挺正
Little Gong, what are you chatting about over there?
小龚，唠啥呢在那？
Get moving.
赶紧的
Biaozi's taking the fall.
彪子接锅了
What do you mean?
啥意思？
Let me tell you,
我告诉你啊
Song Yukun's wife went to the plant hospital this morning and made a scene.
宋玉坤他媳妇早上去厂医院闹去了
Said Huang Liru seduced the factory director.
说黄丽茹勾引厂长
-For real?
-For real.
-真的假的？
-真的
The two of them have been at it a long time.
他俩都好老长时间了
Listen, you two,
我告诉你俩啊
keep it to yourselves, don't spread it around.
自己知道得了，别出去说去
Okay... got it.
行…知道了
Give me a light.
火给我
What are you doing over here? Done pouring the water?
你跑这来干啥呢？ 水倒完了吗？
Done.
倒完了
I figured I'd ask if there's anything else to do.
我寻思问问还有没有别的活
Um... arrange the flowers on the stage nicely,
那啥…你把台上那花再好好摆摆
and once that's done, go over the meeting agenda with them again.
摆完之后把会议流程 再跟他们对一下
-Go on.
-Okay.
-去吧
-行
There's nothing more to say.
没啥好说的
I've thought it all through.
我都想明白了
I definitely can't keep this child.
这孩子我肯定不能要
Let's not be rash, okay?
咱别冲动好不好？
Just give me a little time.
妳稍微给我点时间
I'm not being rash.
我没冲动
I'm getting married.
我要结婚了
Let's end it here.
咱们到此为止吧
Let's not see each other anymore.
以后别见面了
Liru.
丽茹
(Hualin Steel No. 1 Main Plant Workers' Congress)
（桦林钢铁第一总厂职工代表大会）
Workers of Hualin Steel,
桦钢的职工们
today fate brings us together here.
今天我们有缘相聚在这
My feelings are very complicated.
我这个心里很复杂
I have deep feelings for Hualin Steel.
我对桦钢有很深的感情
I believe everyone here feels the same about Hualin Steel as I do.
我相信在座的各位 对桦钢的情感跟我是一样的
Some comrades feel even more deeply than I.
甚至有些同志比我还要深
But today there's a fact I must share with you all.
但今天有个事实我不得不跟大伙说
Hualin Steel's situation right now is not optimistic.
就是桦钢现在的处境不乐观
-The burden is very heavy.
-Master Wang.
-负担非常重
-王师傅
This carriage that is Hualin Steel —
桦钢这驾马车
it can't be pulled any longer.
拉不动了
Where's he up to?
讲到哪了？
Just started.
刚开始
Rambling on about a load of useless stuff.
净扯一堆没有用的
We came just to hear the list, didn't we?
来不就是听名单的吗？
Don't they have to sound the opening gong before the opera?
唱戏之前不得有个开场锣吗？
We know their routine all too well.
他们这套路子咱太熟了
Now is the time for us to give back to Hualin Steel.
现在就是我们回馈桦钢的时候
Some comrades have grievances, and I understand that.
有一些同志有怨言，我可以理解
But once grievances turn into rumors,
但怨言一旦变成谣言
that's fatal.
那是致命的
What are you standing there for?
愣着干啥呀？
Go pour the water.
倒水去
What else I want to say is, some workers —
还有我要说的就是一些职工
for instance, dual-worker households —
比如说双职工
who are genuinely in difficulty,
确实遇到困难的
we must help them in good time.
我们要及时地予以帮助
We must also tackle the issue of raising output and efficiency.
还有就是要解决增产、增效这个问题
That's the focus of our work going forward.
这是我们接下来工作的重点
Win or lose, live life boldly.
看成败，人生豪迈
We must have confidence and resolve.
我们必须要有信心，要有决心
There's no hurdle we can't clear.
没有什么坎是我们过不去的
Enough.
够了
What are you doing?
你干啥呢？
Why'd the mic cut out?
怎么还哑火了呢？
What exactly is between you and Liru?
你到底跟丽茹啥关系？
I'm giving a report. Get down.
我在作报告，下去
You fucking set me up.
你他妈坑我
Gong Biao, don't push your luck. Get down.
龚彪，别给脸不要，下去
Gong Biao, get down.
龚彪，你下来
Get down, now.
你快下来你
Something's off.
不对劲
-Security comrades!
-Fuck you, Song Yukun.
-保卫科的同志
-操你妈的，宋玉坤
-You trying to start a riot?
-Stop it, now.
-你要造反吗你？
-快住手
-Say it, come on.
-What are you doing? Rioting?
-你说呀你
-干什么你？ 你要造反吗你？
Jianchun.
建春
-Somebody!
-Biaozi.
-来人
-彪子
-Biaozi...
-Let go, today I'll...
-彪子…
-撒开，我今天我…
-Get him... what are you doing?
-Biaozi.
-给我…干什么？
-彪子
Have you fucking lost your mind?
你他妈吃错药了你呀？
What do you think you're doing?
你这要干什么？
Outrageous.
太猖狂了
You all right, Director?
没事吧，厂长？
-What are you doing?
-Put your back into it.
-干什么？
-使点劲
-Hit him.
-揍他
-Beat a man to death and you won't pay?
-Harder.
-你们打死人不偿命
-使点劲
I... Jianchun...
我…建春…
That's about enough with the work matters.
工作上的事你差不多行了
Who are you to say? Fine, your call.
你是干啥的？ 听你的
Wait.
不是
If you beat him badly,
你打坏了
won't you be held responsible?
你不得担责任啊？
Wang Xiang, I'm doing this for your sake.
王响，我看你面子
Only for you.
也就是你
Anyone else today, and it wouldn't have worked.
今天换另外一个人都不管用的
All right... that's enough.
好…行了
Jianchun.
建春
Okay.
行
You two keep an eye on him.
你俩盯着点
The meeting's not over.
会没开完
Don't let him back in, you hear?
不能让他进去，听着没有？
Get to it.
赶紧的
I'm giving you face, let me tell you.
我给你面子，我告诉你
Just now some comrades got rather worked up.
刚才有些同志的情绪比较激动
That's understandable.
这个可以理解
After all, our plant now faces a difficult historic choice.
毕竟咱们厂现在面临着 艰难的历史抉择
Talk to me.
你跟我说说
What's it really about?
到底因为啥？
I see everyone's quite concerned about the layoff and furlough list, yes?
我看大家对下岗、待岗人员名单 都比较关心，是吧？
So I'll adjust the agenda on the spot.
那我就临时改改会议进程
I'll announce the layoff and furlough list early.
提前宣布下岗、待岗人员名单
Speaking of layoffs and furloughs,
说到下岗、待岗
the plant office will lead the way.
我们厂办带个头
Plant office layoff:
厂办下岗人员
Gong Biao.
龚彪
Locomotive depot layoffs:
机务段下岗人员
Zhang Youcheng.
张有成
Hao Chenggang.
郝成钢
This suit's no big deal anyway.
这身衣服也没啥大不了的
Li Qing.
李庆
Fang Zhonghua.
方中华
Equipment section layoffs:
设备科下岗人员
Sun Liqiang.
孙立强
Tian Mingzhi.
田明智
What's going on, Master Wang?
怎么回事呀，王师傅？
Jiang Yanquan.
蒋彦全
Comrade Wang Xiang, is there something?
王响同志，有事吗？
You're a real fucking piece of garbage.
你他妈真是个杂碎
-Seen Biaozi?
-He was on stage just now.
-看见彪子了吗？
-刚才还在台上呢
What did you say?
你说啥？
Garbage.
杂碎
From the locomotive depot.
机务段的
Pull them apart...
拉开…
Stop fighting.
别打了
A bunch of fucking useless idiots.
他妈一群废物
What's your security section even good for?
你们保卫科干什么吃的你？
Can't even hold back a few workers.
几个工人都拦不住
Director, don't worry.
厂长，您放心
Anyone who went up on that stage won't get away.
只要是上台的，谁都别想跑
-We'll deal with them one by one.
-Right.
-挨个收拾他
-对
Handle it firmly, make an example.
严肃处理，举一反三
Deal with it firmly.
给我严肃处理
It must be dealt with firmly.
必须严肃处理
Especially that ringleader, Wang Xiang.
尤其是那个带头的王响
I'll deal with him first.
我第一个就收拾他
Calm down.
消消气
Director, is it out of order?
厂长，不走字了？
Get lost.
滚一边去
Who are you two? Who are you looking for?
你俩干啥的？ 找谁呀？
Is Song Yukun in?
宋玉坤在吧？
Look, the director's busy, out you go...
不是，厂长挺忙的，出去…
I'm talking to you two, hear me?
我跟你俩说话呢，听见没有？
Song Yukun, right?
宋玉坤吧？
Hey, just who are you?
不是，你是干啥的你是？
We're from the Municipal Discipline Commission.
我们是市纪委的
You've been reported for embezzling state assets,
有人举报你侵吞国有资产
and for retaliating against workers under the guise of layoffs.
以下岗的名义打击报复工人
Please cooperate with our investigation.
请你配合我们调查
Quick to respond.
出警挺快
Detaining me, are you?
要拘我呀？
Let's go.
来吧
Wang Yang.
王阳
Found him.
找着了
What are you doing? You can't go in.
你干啥？ 这不让进
-I'm going in.
-Comrade, please cooperate.
-我进去
-同志，你配合一下
Let him in.
让他进去
Captain Ma.
马队
Cui.
崔
Is it Wang Yang?
是王阳吗？
There's been a mistake, right?
整错了吧？
It's a mistake, isn't it?
是不是整错了？
Fang He.
方赫
Get up.
起来
What are you doing lying here?
在这躺着干啥？
If you want to sleep, go home and sleep.
乐意睡，回家睡去
Get up.
起来
Be good.
听话
Yang'er.
阳儿
Yang'er, don't scare your dad.
阳儿，你别吓唬爸
Yang'er.
阳儿
Yang'er, get up.
阳儿，你起来
Get up, let's go home.
你起来回家
Yang'er, get up.
阳儿，你起来
Yang'er, let's go home.
阳儿，回家
Dad won't scold you ever again.
爸再也不说你了
Do whatever you want.
你愿意干啥你就干啥
Get up.
起来
Mom's still at home waiting for you.
妈还在家等你呢
You and I still have to go to Beijing.
咱爷俩还得去北京
Yang'er.
阳儿
Yang'er... don't scare me.
阳儿…你别吓唬我
Don't scare me, Yang'er.
你别吓我，阳儿
Yang'er... don't...
阳儿…你别…
Yang'er, don't scare your dad...
阳儿，你别吓唬爸…
Don't scare your dad.
你别吓唬爸
What flowers?
买啥花？
What flowers do people give as gifts?
送人都选啥花呢？
For visiting the sick, usually these — they bloom just in water.
看病人一般这种，插水就能开
And they don't cause allergies.
而且不过敏
Not for a patient — for a friend.
不看病人，送朋友
You know, the... female kind of friend.
就是那种女的那个朋友
Then let me give you a hand.
那我帮你搭一把吧
Okay...
好…
Boss.
老板
-Just these, wrap them up for me.
-Sure.
-就要这些，帮我包一下
-好的
-Sure... let me help him first.
-Okay...
-好的…我先帮他一下啊
-好…
-Buying flowers?
-Buying flowers.
-买花？
-买花
For your girlfriend?
送女朋友？
Just get the same as mine.
你和我整一样的得了
Eleven roses, two lilies.
11朵玫瑰，2朵百合
Is there a meaning to it?
这有什么讲啊？
Whole-hearted devotion, a hundred years of harmony.
一心一意，百年好合
That's a lovely meaning.
这意思可好
Very nice.
挺好
Say, little brother,
老弟，你说
I want to convey a bit of an apology too.
我想再表达一点歉意
Just to say sorry, that sort of thing.
就是道个歉啥的
What flower should I add for that?
再加点什么花呢？
Add some forget-me-nots.
整点勿忘我
Okay.
好
"Don't forget me, don't hold it against me."
别忘了我，别挑我理
Your flowers.
您的花
Thanks, boss.
谢谢呀，老板
-Take care.
-Thanks.
-慢走啊
-谢谢
-Goodbye.
-Okay...
-再见
-好…
Eleven roses,
11朵玫瑰
two lilies,
两枝百合
and extra forget-me-nots.
多加勿忘我
-You got it.
-Extra.
-好咧，好
-多加
Okay.
好
Little brother, need a cab?
老弟，你打车呀？
Here... I'll give you a ride, come on.
来…我拉你，来
Is that all right?
方便吗？
Don't you have somewhere to be?
你不有事吗？
Where are you headed?
你要去哪啊？
To Culture Street to pick someone up.
去文化街接个人
Then hop in, it's right on the way.
那你上来吧，正好顺路
No charge.
不要钱
Thanks for being my advisor.
感谢你给我当参谋
-Then I won't stand on ceremony.
-Good.
-那就不客气了
-好
Here, hold this for me.
来，帮我拿一下
Okay...
好…
-Don't mix them up.
-Okay.
-别弄混了啊
-好
-The one with forget-me-nots is mine.
-Okay.
-勿忘我那个是我的
-好
Here.
来
Off to see your girlfriend?
见女朋友去吧？
Well... not exactly.
也…也不算
We haven't made it official yet.
还没确定关系呢
I plan to bring it up with her today.
今天准备跟她提
I'm a bit unsure.
心里有点没底
No problem.
没问题
Little brother, with your air and bearing,
老弟呀，就你这个精神气质呀
I'm telling you, one look and you're the refined type.
讲话了，一看儒雅
There's no way it won't work out.
没有不成的道理
From your lips to God's ears.
借你吉言
What do you do for work?
干啥工作的？
I used to teach in the academic office at No. 10 Middle School.
以前在十中教务处当老师
Retired last year.
去年退了
Let me tell you, I drive a cab every day,
我跟你说，我天天开计程车
I meet a lot of people,
见的人多
I've got a sharp eye.
眼睛毒
One look and I can tell you're an educated man.
一看你就是个文化人
You teachers,
你们当老师的
your retirement benefits are pretty good, right?
退休待遇是不是挺高啊？
They're all right, I suppose.
这还行吧
Anyway, the pension goes up every year.
反正工资年年都涨
My wife passed early.
我爱人没得早
The kids are all on their own.
儿女也都独立了
Now...
现在…
I don't have big expenses.
没啥大花销
So I get by fairly comfortably.
就算比较从容吧
That's a good situation.
这条件不错
Find yourself a good companion,
再找个好老伴
and your days
小日子
would be just great.
老得劲了
Qiaoyun, don't worry.
巧云，妳别着急
I've got a cab.
打上车了啊
I'll be there soon.
马上就到
Little brother,
老弟
was your... your girlfriend once with Hualin Steel?
你…你女朋友过去是桦钢的吗？
Yes.
是呀
Now she... she runs a massage parlor.
现…现在开家推拿店
Why? You know her?
怎么的？ 你认识啊？
The name sounds familiar.
名听着耳熟
Might recognize her when I see her.
见面兴许能认识
What a coincidence.
那可巧了
She often mentions things about you folks at Hualin Steel.
她老提你们桦钢的事
She just finished her retirement paperwork.
这不刚办完退休嘛
She says she wants to close the massage parlor.
她说想把推拿店给关了
Then the two of us will travel around, see some places.
到时候我俩就各地走一走，旅旅游
Spend our later years together in peace, I suppose.
一起安度晚年吧就算
Driver, turn at the Culture Street intersection.
师傅，文化街路口拐
You... turn up ahead and just pull over.
你…你前面拐过去，给我靠边停就行
She's waiting for me at the roadside.
她在道边等我呢
Went and bought you flowers.
给妳买花去了
These are yours.
这是您的
It was hard to catch a cab over there.
那边不好打车
Luckily I ran into this driver who gave me a lift.
正好遇上这师傅给我捎过来了
He used to be with Hualin Steel too.
他以前也是桦钢的
Isn't that a coincidence?
妳說巧不巧？
Li Qiaoyun.
李巧云
Are you Li Qiaoyun?
是不是李巧云？
Do you remember?
想起来没？
From the locomotive depot.
机务段的
Surname Wang.
姓王
I remember, Master Wang.
我记着，王师傅
I remember.
记着呢
What a coincidence.
巧了
Shall we ride with him, then?
那咱还坐他车吧？
Master Wang and I hit it off nicely.
我和王师傅聊得挺投机的
We're going to Daguang Mall.
我们去大光商场
Would you mind giving us a lift a bit further?
您再捎我们一段，方不方便？
Sure...
方便…
I can't drive you for free this time, though.
这回不能白拉了啊
Okay...
好…
Here, Qiaoyun, flowers for you.
来，巧云，送妳的花
Are you hungry?
妳饿不饿？
Should we eat first, or see the movie first?
一会咱俩是先吃饭，还是先看电影？
Either's fine.
都行
Then let's eat first.
那咱们就先吃饭
Anything you feel like eating?
妳有啥想吃的没有？
Anything's fine.
都行
Okay, let me look it up.
好，我查查
Master Wang.
王师傅
Those flowers of yours are lovely.
你这花挺好看啊
This little brother here helped me pick them.
是我这个老弟帮着选的
Exactly the same as his.
跟他的一模一样
Added some forget-me-nots.
加了点勿忘我
It's just...
就是…
"Don't hold a grudge against me."
别记恨我
A bit of an apology.
有点道歉的意思
Driving the two of us,
那你拉我俩
won't it keep you from delivering your flowers?
不耽误你送花啊？
It won't.
不耽误
That person's also an old-timer from Hualin Steel.
那人也是桦钢的老人
Whether I deliver them or not,
我送不送的
she'll understand what I mean.
她都能明白我的意思
Do I know this person you're giving flowers to?
你送花的这人我认识吗？
You probably do.
应该认识
She worked the weighbridge in the scale house.
她是磅房过磅的
A good person.
人挺好
She's had a hard life.
这辈子挺不容易的
Proud and strong-willed.
要强
But when other women ran into trouble,
可是别的女同志遇着点啥事
they'd always cry and wail.
总是哭啼的
She stayed cheerful.
她乐呵的
Quite admirable.
挺让人佩服的
So you never thought of taking things a step further with her?
那你就没想着跟她往前走一步呢？
How to put it...
怎么回事呢？
It's just, lately I've been through some things.
就是最近我遇着点事
I've come across a lot of us old Hualin Steel folks.
接触不少我们桦钢的老人
And I've realized,
我就发现啊
no matter how they've fared, however their lives turned out,
人家不管过得好坏，活成啥样
they can all look ahead.
都能往前看
But not me.
我就不行
I just can't get past it.
老过不去那个劲
I heard this friend of mine is doing well now.
我听人说我这个朋友现在过得挺好
After the bitter comes the sweet.
苦尽甘来
I'm happy for her.
挺替她高兴的
I just want her to live the rest of her life in comfort.
我就想让她后半辈子过得舒心一点
Not to fret and worry over a little old man like me.
别跟我这个小老头担惊受怕
All bottled up and wronged.
憋了吧屈的
It's not worth it.
犯不上
Master Wang, you're sentimental about the past.
王师傅，你这是念旧
Sentimental, if you want to put it nicely.
说好听是念旧
Really it's just being stubborn to a fault.
其实就是爱钻牛角尖
Not quick in the head.
脑袋不灵活
Pretty annoying.
挺烦人的
Why are you crying, Qiaoyun?
妳怎么哭了，巧云？
It's nothing.
没事
I was just remembering some things from the past too.
我也是想起点过去的事
Take my word.
信我的
Don't dwell on the past.
不想过去的事
What's past, let it stay past.
过去了就让它过去
Look ahead.
往前看
Right.
对
Look ahead.
往前看
Master Wang, how much?
王师傅，多少钱？
No charge, little brother.
不用掏钱了，老弟
Just do me one favor.
有个事拜托一下
Be good to our Qiaoyun from now on.
以后对我们巧云好点
Or us old workmates won't stand for it.
不然我们老工友们不答应你
I will...
一定…
Thank you.
谢谢呀
Qiaoyun, let's get out.
巧云，下车啊
Thank you, Master Wang.
谢谢呀，王师傅
Little brother.
老弟呀
I wish you both well.
祝福你们
-This...
-I'm past my use now.
-这…
-我没用了我
Forget-me-not.
勿忘我啊
Thank you...
谢谢…
Master Wang's a really warm person.
王师傅这人真挺热情
His name is Wang Xiang.
他叫王响
"Xiang" as in "xiangliang" — resounding.
“响亮”的“响”
Biaozi.
彪子
This matter's settled now.
这事就算完了
These few copies are yours.
这几份是你的
Keep them safe.
都拿好了
Give me that license too.
把那证也给我吧
What do you want that license for?
你要这证干啥？
It's void now.
都作废了
I'll... keep it as a memento.
我…我留个纪念
It's got my photo on it.
那上边还有我照片呢
Fine.
得
I've already arranged it with someone.
我都跟人说好了
I'll drive the car over by the end of the month.
月底把车开过去啊
Don't worry.
放心吧
I'll clean it up nice and deliver it to you.
到时候我整干净的，给你送过去
Okay.
行
Thanks.
谢谢啊
(Hualin City Taxi Driver Service Qualification License)
（桦林市计程车汽车驾驶员 服务资格证）
Your sign would look so much better hung over there.
你这牌挂那边多好啊
So much more eye-catching.
多醒目啊
Hung there, people coming from that side can't even see it.
你挂那，从那边过来，人也看不见啊
Who are you?
你谁呀？
Who am I?
我谁呀？
I'm the owner of this shop, who am I?
我这店老板，我谁呀？
Thanks for your hard work.
辛苦了啊
Thanks, boss.
谢谢老板
Here, catch.
接好了
Been too busy lately.
最近太忙了
Haven't come by much.
没怎么过来看
Where's your Boss Huang?
你们黄总呢？
Inside, I take it?
在屋里吧？
All right, you all get to it.
那行，你们好好整吧
Hang it over here.
挂这边啊
Master, mainly you've got to smooth out the edges and corners up top.
师傅，你主要上边 那边边角角得抹好了
-You know? Then let it dry all the way through.
-You got it.
-你知道吗？ 然后得干透啊
-好咧
-Once it's fully dry, do a second coat.
-Sure.
-干透完了抹第二遍
-行
What are you doing here?
你怎么来了？
Coming along quite nicely.
整得挺像样啊
Whatever it is, say it at home; I'm swamped here.
你有啥事回家说吧，我这老忙了
Look at this place, all in a mess.
你瞅这，弄得乱糟糟的
You don't answer my calls, don't reply on WeChat.
我给妳打电话也不接，微信也不回
What's wrong?
怎么的了？
Trying to spring a surprise on me?
想给我整个意外惊喜啊？
What surprise?
什么意外惊喜？
Don't be angry now.
别生气了啊
So petty.
心眼那小呢
Enough, stop the tugging and pulling here.
行了，别在这拉拉扯扯的
What's the matter with you?
干什么玩意？
Is this going to go on forever?
没完没了了？
-What? Stop yanking me, that hurts.
-What's going on, Liru?
-干什么？ 你别老拽我，我疼
-怎么了，丽茹？
Who's this?
这谁啊？
My husband, Gong Biao.
我爱人，龚彪
This is Brother Hao.
这是郝哥
Biaozi?
彪子？
Liru's always mentioning you.
老听丽茹提你
How come you're not out driving today?
你今儿怎么没出车呀？
Who's this?
谁呀？
Brother Hao? A business partner.
郝哥吗？ 合伙人
Brother Hao.
郝哥呀
Quite the stylish one.
挺有派呀
What line of work?
干啥工作的？
A little business here and there.
做点小买卖
Just bought into Boss Huang's place here.
这不刚在黄总这入股嘛
I've got a few repair shops over in Daowai too.
我在道外还有几家维修厂
Anything wrong with your car, just come by.
你的车有啥毛病直接过去
Just mention my name.
提我就行啊
-Here.
-I'm not used to these.
-来
-我抽不惯这个
Nothing's wrong with my car.
我车没问题
What I've got now is a problem with my marriage.
我现在感情有问题
Can you fix that?
能修啊？
What do you mean, Biaozi?
啥意思呀，彪子？
Watch your words.
说话注意点分寸啊
Don't call me Biaozi.
别彪子
Is "Biaozi" for you to say?
彪子是你叫的？
Call me Brother Biao.
叫彪哥
What's this? Why are you bickering with people?
怎么说的？ 跟人吵吵嚷嚷干啥？
What are you staring at? Get back to work.
你看啥看呢？ 干你活
-What's it got to do with him?
-It's fine.
-跟人家有什么关系呀？
-没事
Come on, let's talk outside, come.
来，出来说，来
No, where'd this Brother Hao come from?
不，哪冒出这么个郝哥呀？
What's so great about him?
他哪好他呀？
Acting so arrogant with me.
跟我这嚣张的
What exactly is between you two?
你俩到底啥关系呀？
Do you have amnesia or something?
你是不是有健忘症啊你？
Didn't I just tell you inside?
我里面跟你说没说？
A business partner.
合伙人
He puts up the money, I provide the skills — anything wrong with that?
人家出钱，我出技术，有毛病吗？
Why go into business with him?
妳跟他合啥伙啊？
Isn't building a life together its own partnership, just us two?
那过日子不咱俩合伙吗？
If you're going to think dirty like that, then there's nothing to discuss.
你要是往那脏里想，咱俩就不用唠了
No, Liru.
不是，丽茹
I didn't mean it that way.
我没那意思
What's the matter with you?
干什么玩意？
You ignore my messages just to spite me, don't you?
妳不回我信不就为了气我吗？
Buying the car behind your back — I was in the wrong, true.
我偷摸买车这事确实干得不对
But haven't I sincerely apologized to you already?
我不已经郑重给妳道歉了吗？
Besides, even the worst offense has its limit.
再说杀人不过头点地呢
A married couple quarrels at the head of the bed and makes up at the foot, right?
那夫妻俩不就床头吵吵床尾合吗？
Besides, I've been staying at my brother-in-law's these past few days.
另外，这几天我一直住姐夫家呢
I haven't been anywhere.
我哪都没去
You can be absolutely sure of that.
这点妳绝对放心
I'm not worried.
我没不放心
I couldn't care less.
我压根就不关心
Give me a little more time.
妳再给我点时间
We won't use anyone else's money.
咱不用别人钱了
Biaozi, it's not about money for us.
彪子，咱俩不是钱的事
My divorcing you isn't about money.
我跟你离婚不是钱的事
Then I don't get it — what else is it about?
那我就闹不明白了，妳还因为啥呀？
Because I don't want to be with you anymore.
因为我不想跟你过了
Understand?
听明白没？
Enough. I'm done.
够了，不想过了
Careful...
你慢点…
Let me hold it for you.
我给你捧着吧
Look, your suit's all smudged.
你瞅这西服都蹭脏了
It's fine, it's just work.
没事，干活嘛
What? Something else?
怎的？ 还有事啊？
No.
没有了
I'm heading back.
回去了
Liru.
丽茹
Come home tonight, let's have a proper talk.
晚上回家吧，咱好好聊聊
You're back, Biaozi?
回来了，彪子？
The jackpot hasn't been drawn yet.
大奖还没出呢
Buy a couple more tickets.
再来两注吧
I'm not that lucky.
没那命
Here.
来
Eat up, all of you.
都吃饱点
Full bellies fly far.
吃饱了，飞得远
Are you ever going to clean up your pigeon droppings?
你家那鸽子屎还能不能收拾了？
How many times have I said it?
说多少回了都？
Stinking the place up every single day.
天天整得臭气熏天的
It's affecting the kids' studies.
都影响孩子学习了
Stop nagging.
别吵吵了
Go home and help your kid with homework.
赶紧回家辅导妳孩子学习吧
I'm cleaning it up, aren't I?
这不收拾吗？
Soon you won't be able to smell them even if you wanted to.
以后想闻都闻不着了
Get on with it.
赶紧的吧
Had enough to eat?
吃饱了吗？
Full now?
吃饱了吧？
You're back.
回来了
Haven't made this in years.
多少年不做了
Have a taste — is it still the same?
尝尝，还是那味不？
What is it?
怎么了？
The way you're looking at me gives me the creeps.
妳看得我直发毛
Come on, Biaozi, if something's up, just say it.
不是，彪子，你有啥事你就说吧
Um... they're renovating my shop soon,
那啥…我那店里面一会还装修
I've got to keep an eye on it.
我得盯着
In such a hurry?
那么着急啊？
It's our last meal.
最后一顿饭
Finish it before you go.
吃完再回去吧
What do you mean?
啥意思啊？
I've drawn up a divorce agreement.
我拟了一份离婚协议
Take a look at it later.
妳回头看一眼
I've already signed it.
我已经签完字了
I want nothing.
我啥都不要
The savings, the house — all yours.
存款、房子都归妳
As for the pigeons, they're gone even if you wanted them.
那鸽子妳想要也没有了
I let them all go.
我都放了
No problem, just sign and it's done.
没啥问题，签个字就完事了
Have a bowl of soup, it'll get cold.
喝碗汤吧，一会凉了
All right, I'll serve it.
行了，我盛吧
You never lift a finger normally.
平时啥都不沾手
Liru, I've thought it through, really.
丽茹，我想明白了，真的
All these years,
反正这些年
you've suffered plenty with me.
妳也跟我遭了不少罪
Never got to enjoy much.
也没享着啥福
And I've got nothing to give you.
我也没啥能给妳的
My life's already turned out this way.
反正我这辈子就这样了
I just want you to be well.
就希望妳好
Think you're pretty noble, don't you?
觉得你自己挺伟大吧？
Naturally.
那必须的
A '90s college graduate, after all.
90年代大学生嘛
No good at much else,
别的啥啥不行
but the refined air, that I've got down.
气质这块必须拿捏呀
Hurry and eat, it's getting cold.
赶紧吃吧，凉了
Do me the honor.
给点面子
When does your shop open?
妳店啥时候开呀？
By the end of the year.
年底就能开
What's it called?
叫啥名？
Haven't decided on a name yet.
名没想好呢
You're the educated one — think one up for me.
你挺有文化，你帮我想一个吧
What would I know?
我瞎想啥呀？
Your partner might not go for it anyway.
妳那合伙人也未必答应
All right.
行
I'll say no more.
别的不说了
Today I'll toast with soup in place of wine.
我今天就以汤代酒了
I'll drink first, in your honor.
先干为敬
Don't drink that soup, I made it too salty.
那汤妳别喝了，整咸了
It'll bother your throat.
弄得嗓子不舒服
All right.
行
Anyway, this is settled today.
反正这事今天就定下了
Liru.
丽茹
I wish you happiness.
祝妳幸福
I've left the keys by the door for you.
钥匙我给妳放门口了
Biaozi.
彪子
I thought of a name for your shop.
妳那店名我给妳想了一个
Let's call it "Rumeng" — Like a Dream.
就叫如梦吧
How's that?
怎么样？
All those years we spent together,
咱俩一起过那么多年
it always felt like a dream.
老觉得像作一场梦似的
Now the dream's over.
现在梦醒了
From now on, let's both be well.
以后咱俩都好好的
Both be well.
都好好的
"Rumeng" is a fine name.
就叫如梦挺好
Life is short.
人生苦短
Just like Biaozi said,
就像彪子说那样
life is but a dream.
人生就是一场梦
I learned a saying recently.
最近学了一句话
It goes: of life's disappointments,
叫人生不如意的事
there are eight or nine in ten.
十有八九
Those you can share your heart with
能说几句心里话的人
number but two or three.
也就二三
And as it happens, two bosom friends are right here beside me.
恰好两位知己朋友就在我的身边
That's enough for one life.
人生足矣
Come on, brother-in-law, where'd you pick up this talk?
不是，姐夫，你这从哪学的嗑？
-A whole routine.
-Words from the heart.
-一套一套的
-肺腑之言
"The Place Where Peach Blossoms Bloom."
《桃花盛开的地方》
I dedicate it to you.
送给你们
In that place where the peach blossoms bloom...
在那桃花盛开的地方
Old Ma... what are you doing?
老马头…干啥呢？
Um... calling it a night?
那个…收摊了？
What do you mean, calling it a night?
收啥收摊呀？
I even brought my insulin.
我胰岛素都带来了
I came to spend the night with you.
我陪你睡觉来了
Come on.
来
Nobody leaves without partying all night, come on.
今天不玩一宿不许走啊，来
-Aren't you afraid of getting wrecked?
-Thanks.
-这不怕被干废了呀？
-谢谢
We'll see who ends up wrecked.
谁废还不知道呢
Xiao Li's still at home waiting for me.
小李还在家等着我呢
No need to worry about your dog.
你家狗不用操心
-It was raised on coffee.
-Thanks.
-它喝咖啡长大的
-谢谢
Homeland...
故乡
the place that bore me and raised me...
生我、养我的地方
wherever I stand guard on watch...
无论我在哪里放哨站岗…
This one's good.
这个好
My brother-in-law spared no expense today, you know?
我姐夫今天下血本了，知道不？
I've known this liquor for twenty years.
我认识这酒20年了
I used to have to call this liquor "grandpa."
以前我得管这酒叫大爷
Any longer and it'll be my ancestor.
再不喝以后成我祖宗了
When life gives you joy, drink your fill of it.
人生得意须尽欢
Never mind ancestor or grandpa,
你别管祖宗、大爷
you've just got to drink it, right?
你就得整，是不？
You've got to be happy.
你得高兴
How many years have we sung this lousy song, brother-in-law?
我说这破歌唱多少年了，姐夫
Put on something livelier — have Captain Ma dance one.
你点个刺激点的，你让马队跳一个
-We're all sleepy.
-Okay.
-都困了
-好
Young man, give us this KTV's most electrifying dance number.
小伙，把本KTV 最刺激的舞曲奉献出来
You got it.
好咧
Don't cause any trouble.
别整事啊
And now, presenting Hualin's Dance King,
下面有请桦林舞王
Ma-lon De-bran-sheng, taking the stage in dazzling style!
马龙德兰胜闪亮登场
Not even a dance partner.
也没个舞伴
So lonely.
好孤独啊
Hold on, "Hualin Dance King" — why can't I take that lying down?
不是，他桦林舞王 我怎么那么不服呢？
Back in the disco days, I was somebody at Hualin Tech too.
那当年迪斯科 我也是桦工大有一号啊
Then everybody, come on.
那就全都来着
Come on.
来
Here, keep drinking.
来，接着喝
Here, Captain Ma.
来，马队
Captain Ma.
马队
Come on.
来
No more for me.
不喝了
I'm going home.
回家
Old Ma, you're no fun.
老马头，你这没意思了
Where's your stamina?
啥体力呀？
Always talking yourself up.
还总给我拉硬的
I'm getting old.
我老了
How did we ever get through this life of ours?
你说咱这辈子怎么过来的？
Sometimes I try to recall something,
有时候总想回忆点啥
I rack my brain, and I can't remember a thing.
寻思半天，啥也记不起来了
Biaozi.
彪子
Not remembering is a good thing.
记不住是好事
Some things,
有些事
what should be remembered, we remember.
该记着咱就记着
What should be forgotten, we absolutely forget.
该忘了绝对要忘
Right, Captain Ma?
对不对，马队？
What's this?
怎么的？
Are we really splitting up for good this time?
这回真散伙了？
Splitting up.
散伙
Each to his own home, each to his own mother.
各回各家，各找各妈
I sincerely thank you two good brothers for all your care and effort these past days.
老哥对二位贤弟 这些日子的费心费力表示衷心的感谢
Come on, drink.
来，喝酒
I don't like hearing you talk like that.
我不爱听你说这话
There are things I can't forget.
有些事我忘不了
This isn't your burden alone.
这不是你一个人的事
I'll see this through to the end, for sure.
这事我肯定整到底
That animal...
那畜生啊…
Biaozi.
彪子
When I was young,
我年轻的时候
I sure as hell didn't believe in fate.
特他妈不信命
The older I get, the more I see I was wrong.
我越老越发现我错了
Our fates were all set in stone.
咱这命都给定下来了
Who arranged it?
谁安排的？
Are we just meant to have the fate we've got?
咱这命就活该就这命吧？
Why can't I accept it?
我怎么不服呢？
Bring him here, I'll have a good talk with him.
你叫他过来，我跟他好好唠唠
If I could find him,
我要是能找着他
I'd fight him to the death.
我肯定跟他玩命
Listen to me, brother-in-law.
听我的吧，姐夫
If we're going to live, let's live happily.
活咱就活得乐呵的
We'll deal with it when we find him.
啥时候找着他再说
Here, brother-in-law.
来，姐夫
-Drink.
-喝
-Drink up.
-Drink.
-喝呀
-喝
Brother-in-law... are you two awake?
姐夫…你俩醒没有？
Get up, pull yourselves together.
赶紧起来精神精神
A real man can bend and rise again.
大丈夫能屈能伸
Get up, it's a new day.
起来又是新的一天
Bought you breakfast, wait for me to get back.
给你买早点了，等我回来
Sir, are you extending the room?
老哥，您这还续不？
It's the end of our shift, we've got to clock off.
这我们到点了，得下班了
No, we're done...
不续了…
-Okay, settle the bill?
-The bill...
-好，那买单？
-买单…
Pack these up...
打个包…
-Sure thing.
-Pack them separately.
-好咧，成
-分着放
-Okay.
-Okay...
-好，行
-好…
Captain Ma.
马队
Wake up.
起来了
It's morning.
早晨了
Go home and sleep, Captain Ma.
回家睡去，马队
Captain Ma.
马队
What's a little pain in the wind and rain...
风雨中这点痛算什么
Wipe your tears, don't be afraid...
擦干泪，不要怕
At least we still have dreams...
至少我们还有梦
The results of Sports Lottery draw No. 16129.
体育彩票第16129期的开奖结果
Friends who missed yesterday's live drawing,
错过了昨天开奖直播的朋友
why not take out your ticket
不妨拿出您手中的彩票
and see if this draw's lucky jackpot winner
看看本期大奖的幸运得主
might just be you, there by your radio?
会不会是收音机前的您呢？
All right.
好了
This draw's winning numbers for the front zone of the Grand Lotto
本期大乐透前区开出的中奖号码
are: 07,
分别是07
-08, 19...
-Damn.
-08、19
-我去
30, 35.
30、35
07, 08, 19, 30, 35.
07、08、19、30、35
Now let's look at the winning numbers for the back zone.
现在我们来看后区开出的中奖号码
The first number is 08...
第一个数字是08…
Feeling better?
好点没？
What are you doing?
干啥呢？
Practicing holding your breath?
练闭气呢？
I didn't cancel the banquet.
那酒席我没退啊
Let's pick a good day and get married.
咱俩找个正日子把婚结了吧
Go.
你走吧
What?
啥玩意？
What did you say?
妳說啥呀？
Go.
你走吧
I lied to you.
我骗你了
What? Having second thoughts?
不是，怎么的？ 反悔了？
Don't want to marry me anymore?
不想嫁我了？
You look down on me.
你嫌弃我吧
I lied to you.
我骗你了
Don't bring it up, it's all in the past.
别提了，都翻篇了
From now on, I...
我以后…
I probably can't have children anymore.
可能不能再生孩子了
Then I want you all the more.
那我更得要妳了
No kids, then we'll raise something else.
没孩子就养点别的吧
You really want me?
你真要我？
Why would I lie to you?
骗妳干啥呀？
I even brought you flowers.
我花我都带来了
Your favorite calla lilies.
妳最喜欢的马蹄莲
You picked my flowers again.
你又薅我花了
This time I bought them.
这次是买的
Biaozi.
彪子
No more crying now.
不哭了